Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - [Epitaph on Sir William Williams], Here, foremost in the dangerous paths of fame; 1775; poems.epww
    - Epitaph on Sir Willm. Williams, 1780[?]; mss.0229; poems.epww; 4 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Epitaph on Sir Willm. Williams (p. 113) (Epitaph II. [p. 115]). The poem, which is annotated "This Epitaph (hitherto unpublished) was written at the request of Mr. Fred. Montagu, who intended to have inscribed it on a Monument at Bellisle, at the siege of which this accomplished youth was kill'd, 1761; but for some difficulty attending the erection of it, the design was not executed" on the title page, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - [untitled], [17??]; mss.0058; poems.epww; [1?] transcript in the hand of James Beattie 250 mm x 200 mm; UABD
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 83
      Transcript in the hand of James Beattie, annotated in his hand "Sir William Williams (on whose death these lines were written at the request of his friend Mr Frederick Montagu) was killed in the last war. They were meant to be inscribed on a monument at Bellisle; but from some difficulties attending the execution of it, this design was not executed."
    - Epitaph on Sir W. Williams., [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0061; poems.epww; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 1-2, 5-6] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 47, 83
      Transcript of ll. 1-2 and 5-6 in the hand of John Mitford, here entitled Epitaph on Sir W. Williams. and annotated "Mr. Montague asked him to write the Epitaph on Sir W. Williams and he could not refuse. He did not know much of him...", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 181r.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0057; poems.epww; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 5-6] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of ll. 5-6 in the hand of John Mitford (crossed out), annotated "Mr. Montague asked him to write the Epitaph on Sir W. Williams, he could not refuse. He did not know much of him...", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 32v.
  - [Farewell to Florence], ... oh Faesulae, amoena; 1775; poems.lt08
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 149-150 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 315 (with English prose translation)
    Written at Florence not later than 21 April 1741 and introduced "Eleven months, at different times, have I passed at Florence; and yet (God help me) know not either people or language. Yet the place and the charming prospects demand a poetical farewell, and here it is." Shortly before leaving Florence, Gray sent it in a letter of that date to Richard West. First published, untitled, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 115.
    - [untitled], 1741; mss.0062; poems.lt08; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 48, 83
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 23
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 139.
  - The Fatal Sisters, Now the storm begins to lower; 1768; poems.fsio
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 27-31
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 210-220
    Written at London not later than the beginning of May 1761, based largely on a Latin translation of the original poem preserved in the late 13th-century Njáls Saga, ch. 157. This untitled Old Norse poem is a prophetic account of the Battle of Clontarf, fought on Good Friday 1014. First published in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - [untitled], [1761]; mss.0063; poems.fsio; 3 autograph fair copy, revised 203 mm x 159 mm; MOLI
      Facsimile and description in Verlyn Klinkenborg et al., British Literary Manuscripts, Series I. From 800 to 1800 (New York, 1981), no. 99
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 49, 83-84
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 604, 9
      Autograph fair copy, revised, here untitled but referred to in the preface as a "magic song", beginning "Now the storm begins to lour", with the preface and a prose epilogue beginning "Having finish'd their incantation they tore the web they had woven into twelve pieces...", endorsed in another hand on verso. Bound into a copy of Poems ( 1768 ), following p. 71.
    - Ode (from the Norse-tongue) in the Orcades of Thormodus Torfaeus. Hafniae. 1697. Fol: & also in Bartholinus, [1?] February 1768; mss.0064; poems.fsio; 3 autograph fair copy 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 50, 84
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=136436>
      Autograph fair copy, numbered 7. and here entitled Ode (from the Norse-tongue) in the Orcades of Thormodus Torfaeus. Hafniae. 1697. Fol: & also in Bartholinus, followed by the first line of the original poem "Vitt er orpit fyrir valfalli &c:", including "Advertisement", "Preface", and explanatory notes, used for printer's copy for Poems ( 1768 ), in MS instructions to Dodsley, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768.
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0065; poems.fsio; [3?] autograph fair copy 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Facsimile, showing the last seven lines and the note, on page six of the MS Instructions, the upper three-fourths of which are reproduced, in
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 51, 84
      Autograph fair copy, untitled but numbered 7. and identified from the table of contents as "7. The Fatal Sisters (from the Norse-tongue)", and headed "From the Orcades of Thormodus Torfaeus. Hafniae. 1697. Fol: Vitt er orpit Fyrir valfalli &c:", preceded by a "Prefix", followed by a note on the Valkyriur, and, elsewhere in the MS (p. 9) an advertisement and two notes, in MS Instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - The Song of the Valkyries, 1761; mss.0066; poems.fsio; 2 autograph fair copy, revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 52, 84
      Autograph fair copy, revised, under the heading "Carmina", here entitled The Song of the Valkyries and headed "(see above P: Art: Gothi)", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1067-1068.
    - [untitled], [1761?]; mss.0067; poems.fsio; 1 autograph draft, partial [preface only]; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 53, 84
      Autograph draft of the "Preface", here untitled but under the heading "Gothi", beginning "About the year 1029 Sigurd, Earl of the Orkney-Islands...", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1041.
    - [untitled], [1761?]; mss.0068; poems.fsio; 1 autograph draft, partial [note only]; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 54, 84
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 28n
      Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 216
      Autograph draft of the note on the Valkyries under the heading "Gothi" in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1044.
    - The Song of the weird Sisters Translated from the Norwegian written about 1029., [1761?]; mss.0069; poems.fsio; 3 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton 229 mm x 186 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 55, 84
      Transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton, here entitled, The Song of the weird Sisters Translated from the Norwegian written about 1029.
    - The Fatal Sisters, an Ode. (From the Norse-tongue.) in the Orcades of Thormodus Torfaeus; Hafniae, 1697, Folio and also in Bartholinus, 1780[?]; mss.0223; poems.fsio; 8 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled The Fatal Sisters, an Ode (p. 75) (Ode. VIII. [p. 77]), followed by the first line of the original poem. The poem, the preface of which is here entitled Argument and to which Gray's note on the Valkyriur has been appended, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - From Petrarch. Lib: I: Sonett: 170, Uror io! veros at nemo credidit ignes:; 1814; poems.lt09
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 141-142 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 308-309 (with English prose translation)
    Written probably in 1737 or 1738 when Gray was translating other Italian verse by Tasso and Dante. First published in
    Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. II, 93
    - From Petrarch. Lib: I: Sonett: 170, [1738?]; mss.0070; poems.lt09; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 56, 84
      Autograph fair copy, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 139.
  - [The Gaurus], Nec procul infelix se tollit in aethera Gaurus; 1775; poems.lt10
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 146-149 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 312-315 (with English prose translation)
    Written at Rome in June or early July 1740 while on the Grand Tour with Horace Walpole, and sent from Florence in a letter to Richard West, dated [25 September 1740]. First published, untitled, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), section II, letter no. XXVII.
    - [untitled], July 1740; mss.0071; poems.lt10; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 57, 84
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled, under the heading "Carmina" and annotated "Rome -- July, 1740 just return'd from Naples", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, split over two pages: p. 115 (ll. 1-52) and p. 128 (ll. 53-61).
    - [untitled], June 1740; mss.0072; poems.lt10; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 58, 84
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled, annotated in an unidentified hand "A Fragment in the Stile of Virgil, by T. Gray from Naples".
  - [Gratia magna], Gratia magna tuae fraudi quod Pectore, Nice; 1890; poems.lt11
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 134-137 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 303-306 (with English prose translation)
    Written probably in 1737 or 1738 when Gray was corresponding and exchanging poetry with Richard West who was then at Christ Church, Oxford. First published, untitled, in
    Tovey (ed.), Gray and his Friends (1890), 296-298
    - [untitled], [1738?]; mss.0073; poems.lt11; [?] autograph
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 59, 84
      Starr/Hendrickson, Supplementary Note on Thomas Gray's 'Gratia Magna' (1967), 412
      An unlocated autograph, formerly owned (1967) by collector Gordon N. Ray.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0074; poems.lt11; 3 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 60, 84
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford of an unfinished draft, untitled but headed "MS Poem", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 83-85.
  - [Hymn to Ignorance. A Fragment], Hail, horrors, hail! ye ever-gloomy bowers; 1775; poems.hyig
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 73-74
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 74-77
    Written between March and October 1742 after Gray's arrival in England from the Grand Tour and before his return to Peterhouse, Cambridge. First published, untitled but referred to as a "Hymn or Address to Ignorance", in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 176-177.
    - Fragment of an address or Hymn to Ignorance, [after 1771]; mss.0075; poems.hyig; 3 transcript in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 61, 85
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, here entitled Fragment of an address or Hymn to Ignorance, annotated "...about the year 1743", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1103-1105.
    - Ode to Ignorance. A Fragment, 1780[?]; mss.0231; poems.hyig; 5 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode to Ignorance. A Fragment (p. 1) (Ode. I. [p. 3]). The poem, which is marked with a line of asterisks after l. 38, followed by "caetera desunt", is part of a section called Fragments, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 19), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - Imitated [from Buondelmonte], Lusit amicitiae interdum velatus amictu; 1775; poems.lt14
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 150 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 316 (with English prose translation)
    Written at Florence in the autumn of 1740 and sent in a letter, dated 21 April 1741, to Richard West. First published, untitled, with the original Italian poem in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 115.
    - Imitated, 1741; mss.0076; poems.lt14; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 62, 85
      Autograph fair copy, headed Imitated, together with a copy of the Italian original Spesso Amor sotto la forma, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 139.
  - [Imitated] From Propertius. Lib: 2: Eleg: 1., You ask why thus my loves I still rehearse; 1814; poems.imp2
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 64-67
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 44-47
    Probably written in April of 1742 and sent in a letter to Richard West, [23 April 1742]. First published, except ll. 1-30, in
    Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. II, 87-89
    , published in full in
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. i, 153
    - Lib: 2: Eleg: 1: To Mecaenas, [23 April 1742]; mss.0077; poems.imp2; [?] autograph fair copy; NYPL
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 63, 85
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 105, vol. i, 196-199 (subscription required)
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 613, 10, Sotheby's sale (12 August 1847), lot 87(?), 26, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 245, 74
      Autograph fair copy, headed Lib: 2: Eleg: 1: To Mecaenas, sent in a letter to Richard West, [23 April 1742].
    - From Propertius. Lib: 2: Eleg: 1. To Mecaenas, April 1742; mss.0078; poems.imp2; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 64, 85
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 24
      Autograph fair copy, under the heading "Carmina", here entitled From Propertius. Lib: 2: Eleg: 1. To Mecaenas, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 254-255.
    - To Mecaenas, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0079; poems.imp2; 2 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 1-30] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 65, 85
      Transcript of ll. 1-30, here entitled To Mecaenas, in the hand of John Mitford, headed "Propertii Eleg. 1. Lib. 2" and annotated "The first 30 Lines...are here supplied from Grays MS", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 77-78.
  - Imitated from Propertius, Lib: 3: Eleg: 5:, Love, gentle power, to peace was e'er a friend:; 1814; poems.imp3
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 67-69
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 25-27
    Written at London in December 1738. First published, except ll. 1-4 and 57-58, as Propertius. Lib.3.Eleg.4 in
    Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. II, 85-86
    , ll. 1-4 first published in
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. i, 151
    - Imitated from Propertius, Lib: 3: Eleg: 5:, December 1738; mss.0080; poems.imp3; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 66, 85
      Autograph fair copy, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 96-97.
  - [Impromptus], Here lies Mrs Keene the Bishop of Chester, [etc.]; 1828 and 1884; poems.impr
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 81-82
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 278-279
    These epigrams, subsumed under the work title [Impromptus], were composed possibly at a single point in time between 1753 and 1770. First published in
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. i, 140-141
    , except One day the Bishop having offered..., first published in Joseph Cradock, Literary and Miscellaneous Memoirs (London, 1828), iv 224.
    - And this upon his Lady --, [between 1753 and 1770]; mss.0081; poems.impr; 1 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton 205 mm x 163 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 67, 85
      Transcript, in the hand of Thomas Wharton, here beginning "Here lies Mrs. Keene [...] Bishop of Chester".
    - A Couplet by Mr. Gray, [between 1753 and 1770]; mss.0082; poems.impr; 1 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton 99 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 68, 85
      Transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton.
    - Extempore by Mr. Gr[ay]. on Dr. K[eene]. B[ishop]. of C[hester]., [between 1753 and 1770]; mss.0083; poems.impr; 1 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton 205 mm x 163 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 69, 85
    - Impromptu by Mr. Gray going out of Raby Castle, [between 1753 and 1770]; mss.0084; poems.impr; 1 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton 99 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 70, 85
    - one day the Bishop having offered to give a Gentleman a Goose Mr. Gr[ay]. composed his Epitaph, thus., [between 1753 and 1770]; mss.0085; poems.impr; 1 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton, title revised 205 mm x 163 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 71, 86
  - In D[iem]: 29am Maii, Bella per Angliacos plusquam civilia campos; 1884; poems.lt15
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 125-127 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 296-297 (with English prose translation)
    Composed as an undergraduate exercise at Cambridge, possibly in 1735. First published in
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. i, 166
    - In D[iem]: 29am Maii, [1735?]; mss.0087; poems.lt15; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 73, 86
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 32
      Autograph fair copy signed "Gray".
  - In 5tam Novembris, Lis anceps, multosque diu protracta per annos; 1884; poems.lt16
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 127-129 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 297-299 (with English prose translation)
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. i, 167
    - In 5tam Novembris, [1735?]; mss.0086; poems.lt16; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 72, 86
  - Inscription for a Wood in a Park, Ἁζόμενος πολύθηρον ἑκηβόλου ἄλσος Ἀνάσσας; 1775; poems.inaw
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 189 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 345 (with English prose translation)
    Written in May 1742. First published, untitled but introduced as "an inscription for a wood joining to a park of mine", in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), section III, letter X. Mason is the only source for this (probably conflated) letter, dated [27 May 1742], in which Gray originally sent the poem to Richard West.
    - Inscription for a Wood in a Park, May 1742; mss.0088; poems.inaw; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 74, 86
      Autograph fair copy in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 278.
  - [Invitation to Mason], Prim Hurd attends your call and Palgrave proud; 1853; poems.inma
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 82
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 257-258
    Written at Cambridge not later than 8 January 1768, when Gray sent it in a letter to William Mason. First published, untitled and beginning "Weddell attends your call...", in
    Mitford (ed.), Correspondence of Gray and Mason (1853), 412
    - [untitled], 8 January 1768; mss.0090; poems.inma; [1?] autograph; NYPL
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 75, 86
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 461, vol. iii, 992-995 (subscription required)
      Autograph, here untitled, in a letter to William Mason, 8 January 1768.
    - Lines, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0091; poems.inma; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 76, 86
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, here entitled Lines, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 184r.
    - Lines, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0209; poems.inma; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 86
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford (crossed out), here entitled Lines, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 31r.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0089; poems.inma; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 2, 8] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of ll. 2 and 8 (crossed out) in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 119.
  - [Latin exercise from the Tatler], ... pluviaeque loquaces; 1814; poems.lt17
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 112 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 285 (with English prose translation)
    Composed as a school exercise at Eton, possibly in 1731. First published in
    - [untitled], November 1805; mss.0092; poems.lt17; 1 transcript in the hand of Norton Nicholls; ETON
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 77, 86
      Transcript, untitled, in the hand of Norton Nicholls, in his MS Reminiscences of Gray, 5.
  - [Latin verses at Eton], Pendet Homo incertus gemini ad confinia mundi; 1882 and 1884; poems.lt18
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 117-121 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 290-293 (with English prose translation)
    Composed as a school exercise at Eton between February 1733 and September 1734. First published, in part and untitled, in
    Gosse, Gray (1882), 6-7
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. i, 163
    as "Play Exercise at Eton".